<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:base="https://wirtaw.github.io/blog" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Poplavskij Vladimir blog</title>
    <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/feed.xml</link>
    <atom:link href="https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <description>English</description>
    <language>en</language>
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Fixing JNLP `libnsl.so.1` Error on Fedora Linux</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/fedora-jnlp-libnsl-fix/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When attempting to launch Java Web Start (JNLP) applications on recent Fedora Linux installations, experienced users may encounter a &lt;code&gt;javaws&lt;/code&gt; execution error similar to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;javaws: error while loading shared libraries: libnsl.so.1: cannot open shared object file: No such file or directory
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This issue typically arises because the &lt;code&gt;libnsl&lt;/code&gt; (Network Services Library) package, while crucial for some legacy Java applications or specific JDK components, is no longer a default dependency or is deprecated in its traditional form on modern Linux distributions like Fedora. Consequently, a clean JDK installation might not include this library by default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Solution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The resolution is straightforward: explicitly install the &lt;code&gt;libnsl&lt;/code&gt; package using DNF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Install &lt;code&gt;libnsl&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;
Execute the following command in your terminal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-bash&quot; tabindex=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;/span&gt; dnf &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;install&lt;/span&gt; libnsl&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rerun Your JNLP Application:&lt;/strong&gt;
After the &lt;code&gt;libnsl&lt;/code&gt; package is installed, retry launching your &lt;code&gt;.jnlp&lt;/code&gt; file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-bash&quot; tabindex=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;javaws start.jnlp&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application should now execute without the &lt;code&gt;libnsl.so.1&lt;/code&gt; error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Context and Explanation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;libnsl&lt;/code&gt; library historically provided an interface for network services, including functionalities related to NIS (Network Information Service). While its direct role has diminished in modern system architectures, certain older applications, or specific implementations within the Java Development Kit (JDK), might still carry dependencies on it. When these applications are invoked on systems where &lt;code&gt;libnsl&lt;/code&gt; is not present, the &lt;code&gt;javaws&lt;/code&gt; binary (part of the JDK) fails to load due to the missing shared object. Manually installing it ensures all necessary dependencies are met for legacy Java Web Start applications to function correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fix is applicable across various Fedora versions where this dependency omission might occur, ensuring smooth operation of JNLP applications for those requiring them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2026 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/fedora-jnlp-libnsl-fix/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The Power of Not Having an Opinion Online</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/power-of-not-having-an-online-opinion/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;You don’t have to have an opinion about everything on the internet.
Some things are simply none of your business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In today’s hyper-connected world, we feel pressured to weigh in on every trending topic. However, true digital freedom comes from realizing that your silence is just as valuable as your voice. Protect your peace by choosing what deserves your energy and what doesn’t.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 16:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/power-of-not-having-an-online-opinion/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>9 Behavioral Signs of Truly Promising People</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/9-behavioral-signs-of-truly-promising-people/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The importance of your &lt;strong&gt;social circle&lt;/strong&gt; is obvious. However, how to find &lt;strong&gt;valuable&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;promising people&lt;/strong&gt; is an open question. Here is a selection of telling behavioral signs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They are not dragged down by their environment or desires.&lt;/strong&gt; They are independent and know how to decline, reasonably adhering to their priorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They don’t chase the crowd.&lt;/strong&gt; They look at things a little differently. They respect the concept of &lt;strong&gt;“individuality.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They are not afraid to ask questions.&lt;/strong&gt; They fuel their curiosity and are open to discussion. They don’t aggressively try to impose their views as the only correct ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They don’t participate in small talk and meaningless chatter.&lt;/strong&gt; They don’t care what someone is cooking for dinner, who is dating whom, what someone wore, or what a celebrity said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They prefer solitude to big parties.&lt;/strong&gt; They understand the difference between false satisfaction and true pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They are easily irritated by stupid, aggressively insistent, and toxic people.&lt;/strong&gt; They avoid such people at all costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They know how to explain things easily and clearly.&lt;/strong&gt; They are expressive with their ideas and can make sketches and diagrams if needed for clarification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They avoid superficial knowledge.&lt;/strong&gt; They study things from different angles and genuinely enjoy unfamiliar, alternative points of view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you stumble upon someone who fits the description of at least 2-3 points, that is the person you need. Their company will help you achieve success faster. Accordingly, the more such people in your environment, the better.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/9-behavioral-signs-of-truly-promising-people/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Why You&#39;re Stuck: 7 Reasons to Stop and Start Moving</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/why-youre-stuck-personal-growth/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Each of us has certainly had a moment in life when we felt like we were standing still. We dream of great things, we make plans, but for some reason, reality doesn’t keep up with our ambitions. This article isn’t meant to demotivate you, but to shed light on uncomfortable truths that may be the key to unlocking your true potential. Prepare to confront the seven reasons that may be the source of your lack of progress. Ready for an honest conversation with yourself?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;You haven’t lost enough.&lt;/em&gt; You’re too comfy in your average life and don’t even try. You talk about learning new things instead of actually doing them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;You care too much what others think.&lt;/em&gt; You adjust yourself to fit in, focusing on what you own instead of what you do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;You think you’re smarter than you are.&lt;/em&gt; You’ve just learned the same stuff as everyone else to pass tests, but real knowledge comes from real life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;You don’t read.&lt;/em&gt; You only read what you have to, or nothing at all. You’d rather watch TV than learn something new or understand different perspectives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;You’re not curious.&lt;/em&gt; You just soak up whatever news is spoon-fed to you, never questioning anything or digging deeper.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;You don’t ask questions.&lt;/em&gt; You don’t challenge authority or even yourself. You just survive in monotony.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The truth pisses you off.&lt;/em&gt; You’re living with your head in the clouds, ignoring reality, and you’re probably annoyed by this article right now. You’re the only one stopping yourself from doing awesome stuff.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://raymmar.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;Raymmar Tirado&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What dou You think about these reasons?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/why-youre-stuck-personal-growth/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Helpful Fedora Resources: Manage Your Linux System with Ease</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/list-fedora-useful-links/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to our comprehensive collection of helpful resources designed to make managing your Fedora Linux system straightforward and efficient. Whether you’re a new user looking for installation guidance or an experienced administrator seeking advanced tips, this page offers a curated selection of articles, tutorials, and tools. Dive in to learn how to master package management, configure your desktop, troubleshoot common issues, and unlock the full potential of your Fedora workstation or server. We aim to equip you with the knowledge and resources necessary to confidently navigate and optimize your Fedora experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;List of the Fedora links:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/fix-dnf-transaction-failed/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;Fix Fedora “Transaction Failed” Updates: Beginner’s Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/fedora-jnlp-libnsl-fix/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;Fixing JNLP &lt;code&gt;libnsl.so.1&lt;/code&gt; Error on Fedora Linux&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/list-fedora-useful-links/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Fix Fedora &quot;Transaction Failed&quot; Updates: Beginner&#39;s Guide</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/fix-dnf-transaction-failed/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;So, you’re updating your Fedora Linux system, and suddenly, DNF throws a “Transaction failed” error, specifically mentioning file conflicts like those pesky VLC plugins. Don’t sweat it! This article is your friendly guide to understanding and fixing these common update problems, even if you’re new to Linux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problem:&lt;/strong&gt;  Your Fedora update failed with a message similar to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-js&quot; tabindex=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-js&quot;&gt;Transaction failed&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; Rpm transaction failed&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; file &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;usr&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;lib64&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;vlc&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;plugins&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;codec&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;libfaad_plugin&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;so from install &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt; vlc&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;plugins&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;base&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;.21&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;24&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;fc41&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;x86_64 conflicts &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;with&lt;/span&gt; file from &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;package&lt;/span&gt; vlc&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;plugins&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;freeworld&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;.21&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;fc41&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;x86_64&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Understanding the Error:&lt;/strong&gt; This error indicates that two different packages are trying to install the exact same file (&lt;code&gt;/usr/lib64/vlc/plugins/codec/libfaad_plugin.so&lt;/code&gt;) on your system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;vlc-plugins-base&lt;/code&gt;: This is likely the official Fedora package for basic VLC plugins.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;vlc-plugins-freeworld&lt;/code&gt;: This package is almost certainly from the RPM Fusion Free repository, which provides multimedia codecs and other software not included in Fedora due to licensing restrictions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conflict arises because both packages contain &lt;code&gt;libfaad_plugin.so&lt;/code&gt;, which is a plugin for AAC audio decoding. Since RPM Fusion Free often provides more comprehensive multimedia support, it’s common to have both, leading to this conflict during updates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Goal:&lt;/strong&gt;  To resolve this, you need to ensure that only &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; version of the conflicting package (or the package providing the conflicting file) is installed. In most cases, if you’re using RPM Fusion, you’ll want to prioritize the RPM Fusion version as it often provides broader codec support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Method 1: Directly Remove the Conflicting Fedora Package (Recommended)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This method involves removing the &lt;code&gt;vlc-plugins-base&lt;/code&gt; package, which is likely the one causing the conflict with the more feature-rich &lt;code&gt;vlc-plugins-freeworld&lt;/code&gt; from RPM Fusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identify the conflicting packages:&lt;/strong&gt; The error message explicitly states them:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;vlc-plugins-base-1:3.0.21-24.fc41.x86_64&lt;/code&gt; (likely from Fedora’s official repositories)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;vlc-plugins-freeworld-3.0.21-2.fc41.x86_64&lt;/code&gt; (from RPM Fusion)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remove the&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;vlc-plugins-base&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;package:&lt;/strong&gt; Since &lt;code&gt;vlc-plugins-freeworld&lt;/code&gt; is intended to provide the necessary VLC plugins (and often supersedes &lt;code&gt;vlc-plugins-base&lt;/code&gt; in functionality), we can remove the &lt;code&gt;vlc-plugins-base&lt;/code&gt; package directly. DNF should handle the dependencies by letting &lt;code&gt;vlc-plugins-freeworld&lt;/code&gt; take over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-js&quot; tabindex=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-js&quot;&gt;sudo dnf remove vlc&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;plugins&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;base&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What to expect:&lt;/strong&gt;  DNF will list the &lt;code&gt;vlc-plugins-base&lt;/code&gt; package for removal. It might also show that &lt;code&gt;vlc&lt;/code&gt; (the main VLC player package) might be re-evaluated to depend on &lt;code&gt;vlc-plugins-freeworld&lt;/code&gt; if it doesn’t already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Review the output carefully.&lt;/strong&gt;  Ensure it’s only removing &lt;code&gt;vlc-plugins-base&lt;/code&gt; and potentially adjusting VLC’s dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If prompted, type&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;y&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;and press Enter&lt;/strong&gt; to confirm the removal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;3&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clean DNF metadata (optional but recommended):&lt;/strong&gt; After removing packages, it’s good practice to clean DNF’s cache.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-js&quot; tabindex=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-js&quot;&gt;sudo dnf clean all&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;4&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Retry the system update:&lt;/strong&gt; Now that the problematic &lt;code&gt;vlc-plugins-base&lt;/code&gt; package is removed, try the system update again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-js&quot; tabindex=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-js&quot;&gt;sudo dnf update &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;--&lt;/span&gt;refresh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This should now complete successfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Method 2: Reinstalling VLC to Ensure RPM Fusion Dominance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Method 1 doesn’t fully resolve it, or if you want to ensure VLC is entirely sourced from RPM Fusion, you can reinstall it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remove all VLC-related packages:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will remove both the Fedora and RPM Fusion versions of VLC and its plugins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-js&quot; tabindex=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-js&quot;&gt;sudo dnf remove &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&#39;vlc*&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review the list carefully! Make sure you’re not removing anything critical that you don’t intend to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clean DNF metadata:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-js&quot; tabindex=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-js&quot;&gt;sudo dnf clean all&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Install VLC (it should pull from RPM Fusion if enabled):&lt;/strong&gt; If RPM Fusion Free is correctly enabled, &lt;code&gt;dnf install vlc&lt;/code&gt; should pull the RPM Fusion version of &lt;code&gt;vlc&lt;/code&gt; and its associated &lt;code&gt;vlc-plugins-freeworld&lt;/code&gt; by default, as RPM Fusion packages often have higher priority or specific dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-js&quot; tabindex=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-js&quot;&gt;sudo dnf install vlc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verify during installation:&lt;/strong&gt;  DNF should indicate that it’s installing &lt;code&gt;vlc&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;vlc-plugins-freeworld&lt;/code&gt;. Look at the “From repo” column in the transaction summary to confirm the packages are coming from &lt;code&gt;rpmfusion-free&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;rpmfusion-free-updates&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Retry the system update:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-js&quot; tabindex=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-js&quot;&gt;sudo dnf update &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;--&lt;/span&gt;refresh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you’re ready to tackle “Transaction failed” messages like a pro! This guide walked you through solving common dnf update problems in Fedora Linux, giving you the confidence to maintain your system with ease.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/fix-dnf-transaction-failed/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Helpful Resources to Learn JavaScript on GitHub</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/list-js-useful-links/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to me curated list of excellent GitHub repositories that can help you learn JavaScript, from the very basics to advanced concepts. GitHub is a treasure trove of learning materials, code examples, and interactive projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;List of the JavaScript links:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sorrycc/awesome-javascript&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;Awesome JavaScript&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/getify/You-Dont-Know-JS&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;You-Dont-Know-JS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/denysdovhan/wtfjs&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;Wtfjs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mbeaudru/modern-js-cheatsheet&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;Modern JS Cheatsheet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/HowProgrammingWorks/Book/blob/master/content/en/Index.md&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;HowProgrammingWorks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/trekhleb/javascript-algorithms&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;JavaScript Algorithms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ryanmcdermott/clean-code-javascript&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;clean-code-javascript&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sindresorhus/awesome-npm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;Awesome npm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/tc39&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;Ecma International, Technical Committee 39 – ECMAScript&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/list-js-useful-links/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Unmasking Neuroticism: 5 Traps to Recognize in Yourself &amp; Others</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/understanding-the-5-traps-of-neuroticism/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever felt a persistent unease, a gnawing feeling that something isn’t quite right, even when outwardly everything seems fine? Or perhaps you’ve observed patterns in others that just don’t add up? It’s possible you’re encountering the subtle, yet powerful, influence of neuroticism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neuroticism, at its core, is often a consequence of unresolved inner conflicts. It’s a complex psychological landscape where our internal struggles project outwards, sometimes twisting our perceptions and interactions in unexpected ways. Today, we’re going to explore five common “traps” that individuals prone to neurotic patterns often fall into, and crucially, how to recognize them in yourself or those around you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. The Claim to Love: When Connection Becomes a Crutch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all seek love and connection, but for a neurotic individual, the very definition of love can become distorted. What might be labeled as “love” is often something else entirely – a desperate need, a parasitic reliance, or a desire for possession.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How it manifests:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Needing others to live your life&lt;/strong&gt;: An inability to function independently, relying on another person to fulfill basic needs or provide a sense of purpose. It’s not about shared life, but a fundamental inability to live one’s own life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Parasitic existence&lt;/strong&gt;: Depending on someone else to meet your needs because you’re unable or unwilling to satisfy them yourself. This isn’t mutual support; it’s a one-sided drain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possession for prestige&lt;/strong&gt;: A desire to “own” another, especially if that person holds significant power, prestige, or wealth. The perceived “love” is less about the individual and more about what they represent for your own self-importance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Understanding the impact&lt;/strong&gt;: This trap leads to relationships built on unstable foundations, often causing immense strain and dissatisfaction for both parties. It’s a love that suffocates rather than liberates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2. The Claim to Kindness: Submissiveness Masquerading as Virtue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kindness is a beautiful trait, but like love, it can be misconstrued within a neurotic framework. Here, what appears as “kindness” can actually be a deep-seated submissiveness, a suppression of genuine feelings driven by fear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How it manifests&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Suppressed aggression&lt;/strong&gt;: Rather than expressing legitimate anger or frustration, a neurotic individual might repress these aggressive impulses out of an overwhelming fear of judgment or rejection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Obsequious behavior&lt;/strong&gt;: An excessive desire to please, even at personal cost, not out of true altruism but from a desperate need for approval. This isn’t genuine empathy; it’s a strategic move to avoid disapproval.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Understanding the impact&lt;/strong&gt;: This trap prevents authentic self-expression and can lead to resentment brewing beneath a facade of niceness. It also makes it difficult for others to truly connect, as the kindness feels more like a performance than a heartfelt gesture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3. The Claim to Omniscient Interest: When Intellect Dominates Emotion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some neurotic individuals, particularly those disconnected from their feelings and emotions, there’s a strong belief that everything can be solved through pure reason. This often translates into a facade of knowing everything or being intensely interested in a wide array of topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How it manifests&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Over-reliance on intellect&lt;/strong&gt;: A conviction that logical analysis can resolve all problems, often dismissing the role of emotions, intuition, or interpersonal dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Profession as a shield&lt;/strong&gt;: Dedication to a profession or cause, not for its inherent value, but as a means to achieve material well-being, prestige, or power. The true motivation is hidden, even from oneself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Surface-level engagement&lt;/strong&gt;: A broad, but often shallow, interest in many things, serving as a way to avoid deeper emotional introspection or genuine vulnerability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Understanding the impact&lt;/strong&gt;: This trap can create an emotional vacuum, leading to a life that feels intellectually rich but emotionally unfulfilling. It can also make it challenging for others to form deep connections, as genuine emotional exchange is avoided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;4. The Claim to Honesty and Justice: Aggression Dressed as Integrity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This trap is more common in aggressive neurotic types. What they present as unwavering honesty and a commitment to justice is often a thinly veiled expression of their own aggression, disguised as moral superiority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How it manifests&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brutal “honesty”&lt;/strong&gt;: The inability to “sugarcoat” or be tactful is presented as a virtue, but it often serves as an outlet for hostility, intended to demean or put others down rather than to offer constructive truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“No” as a weapon&lt;/strong&gt;: Saying “no” is not an assertion of healthy boundaries or strength, but a desire to humble, suppress, or undermine others. It’s about control, not conviction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Moral grandstanding&lt;/strong&gt;: A tendency to loudly declare their own rectitude while aggressively pointing out the perceived flaws or injustices of others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Understanding the impact&lt;/strong&gt;: This trap creates a toxic environment, eroding trust and fostering conflict. It’s not about genuine integrity; it’s about using the guise of honesty to assert dominance and express aggression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;5. The Claim to Suffering: Unconscious Motives Behind Misery&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neurotic individuals are prone to suffering, but this suffering often feels beyond their control, or at least, its true origins are obscured. To an external observer, their misfortunes might seem exaggerated or overly dramatized. However, there are often hidden motives behind this suffering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How it manifests&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A cry for attention/support&lt;/strong&gt;: Suffering can be an unconscious plea for notice, care, or validation from others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Misattributing the cause&lt;/strong&gt;: A neurotic person might believe they are suffering due to guilt, when in reality, the pain stems from not living up to an idealized self-image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Loneliness masked as heartbreak&lt;/strong&gt;: Believing one is suffering from unrequited love, when the true underlying cause is an inability to tolerate solitude due to an internal fragmentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exaggerated drama&lt;/strong&gt;: While the pain is real to the sufferer, their description of it often appears disproportionate to the actual events, leading others to feel confused or exhausted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Understanding the impact&lt;/strong&gt;: This trap can lead to a cycle of perpetual victimhood, where genuine self-understanding and growth are hindered by unconscious manipulation or misinterpretation of one’s own pain. It also makes it difficult for others to offer effective support, as the true needs are not being articulated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Recognizing the Threads of Neuroticism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These five traps, while distinct, often interweave, leading to complex moral dilemmas and interpersonal challenges for the neurotic individual. They are, ultimately, consequences of unresolved internal conflicts – a person split into parts, unable to fully integrate their experiences and emotions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding these patterns is the first step towards untangling them. If you recognize these traits in yourself, it’s an invitation to explore your inner landscape with curiosity and compassion. If you see them in others, it can foster a deeper understanding, allowing you to interact with greater awareness and empathy. The path to breaking free from these invisible chains begins with recognition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Source&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/psiholog_natakoshulko/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;psiholog_natakoshulko&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jun 2025 16:18:57 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/understanding-the-5-traps-of-neuroticism/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Cynical Truths: Uncomfortable Realities About Life and Relationships</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/cynical-truths/</link>
        <description>&lt;picture&gt;
          &lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/img/cynical-truths-600w.webp 600w, https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/img/cynical-truths-900w.webp 900w&quot; sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;source type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; srcset=&quot;https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/img/cynical-truths-600w.jpeg 600w, https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/img/cynical-truths-900w.jpeg 900w&quot; sizes=&quot;(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/img/cynical-truths-600w.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;900&quot; height=&quot;900&quot; alt=&quot;Uncomfortable Realities About Life and Relationships&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction to Cynicism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cynicism, at its core, is a philosophy rooted in questioning societal norms and perceived truths. It’s about stripping away illusions and facing the world with a critical, often skeptical, eye. While it can be seen as pessimistic, cynicism can also be a pathway to a more authentic and self-aware existence. Cynics value virtue and reason, often rejecting conventional desires for wealth, power, and fame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;11 Cynical Truths&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By constantly forgiving everyone, you help evil to establish itself in impunity.&lt;/strong&gt; Turning a blind eye to wrongdoing only allows it to flourish.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exaggerated point: God will not call you.&lt;/strong&gt; You are responsible for your actions and their consequences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Life failures are a necessity.&lt;/strong&gt; They are inevitable and provide valuable lessons for growth.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Example:&lt;/em&gt; Failing a test teaches you the importance of preparation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Money, no matter how you look at it, is the main thing.&lt;/strong&gt; Financial stability often dictates opportunities and quality of life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Even the biggest failure has an excuse.&lt;/strong&gt; People will always find a way to rationalize their shortcomings.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Example:&lt;/em&gt; Blaming a bad economy for a failed business venture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Always say yes” is not a good rule.&lt;/strong&gt; Setting boundaries is crucial for self-preservation and prevents exploitation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You are not the first in line for the injustice of this world.&lt;/strong&gt; Suffering is a universal experience, and recognizing this can foster empathy.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Example:&lt;/em&gt; Witnessing discrimination highlights systemic inequalities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Everyone wears masks.&lt;/strong&gt; People present different versions of themselves depending on the situation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s worth reviewing your friends list.&lt;/strong&gt; Not all relationships are beneficial, and some may be detrimental to your well-being.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Example:&lt;/em&gt; Cutting ties with friends who consistently bring negativity into your life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No one thinks the same way as you.&lt;/strong&gt; Embrace individuality and understand that perspectives vary widely.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Every person uses you in their own way.&lt;/strong&gt; Recognizing this doesn’t have to be negative, but it’s important to be aware of the dynamics in your relationships.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Example:&lt;/em&gt; A colleague seeking your expertise to advance their own project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These cynical truths may seem harsh, but they offer a clear-eyed perspective on the realities of life. By acknowledging these truths, you can navigate the world with greater awareness, protect yourself from manipulation, and make more informed decisions. Embracing a bit of cynicism can lead to a more authentic and resilient existence.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/cynical-truths/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The Double-Edged Sword of Desire: Why &quot;Be Careful What You Wish For&quot; is Timeless Wisdom</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/be-careful-what-you-wish-for-timeless-wisdom/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“That’s a big takeaway from history, and it leads to a realization that will always be true: Be careful what you wish for.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;– “Same as Ever: A Guide to What Never Changes” &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Morgan-Housel/e/B084ZNV1LR&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;Morgan Housel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This powerful quote distills a truth as old as humanity itself. We often chase desires with unwavering focus, convinced that their attainment will bring ultimate happiness. Yet, history, personal experience, and profound philosophical traditions consistently reveal a paradox: getting exactly what we want can sometimes lead to unforeseen difficulties, deeper dissatisfaction, or even regret. Both Stoicism and Mindfulness offer invaluable frameworks for understanding this intricate relationship with our desires, guiding us toward a more discerning and peaceful approach to life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stoicism: Mastering the Inner Citadel Against External Desires&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stoicism, an ancient philosophy focused on virtue, reason, and living in harmony with nature, provides a robust framework for understanding the pitfalls of unexamined desires. Its core principle, the &lt;strong&gt;Dichotomy of Control&lt;/strong&gt;, teaches us to distinguish between what is within our power (our thoughts, judgments, and actions) and what is not (external events, other people’s opinions, health, wealth). Wishing excessively for things outside our control is, to a Stoic, a direct path to suffering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, consider the &lt;strong&gt;desire for fame or public recognition&lt;/strong&gt;. You might pour your energy into a creative project, dreaming of accolades and widespread appreciation. A Stoic would caution against this fervent wish. Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;External Dependency:&lt;/strong&gt; Fame is an external “indifferent.” It’s not inherently good or bad, and crucially, it’s not something you can control. You can create the art, but you can’t control how others react to it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vulnerability to Fortune:&lt;/strong&gt; If your peace of mind hinges on public approval, you become enslaved to the fickle whims of others. What if the project flops? What if success brings unwanted scrutiny or pressure? Seneca, a prominent Stoic, warned extensively about the dangers of seeking popularity, as it often compromises one’s integrity and inner peace.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compromising Virtue:&lt;/strong&gt; The intense longing for external validation can subtly erode your commitment to virtue. You might find yourself making choices based on what’s popular rather than what’s right or authentic to your craft.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of wishing for fame, a Stoic would advise internalizing your desires: wish to &lt;strong&gt;produce your best work&lt;/strong&gt;, to &lt;strong&gt;act with integrity&lt;/strong&gt;, and to &lt;strong&gt;apply yourself diligently&lt;/strong&gt;. True satisfaction comes from the virtuous effort itself, not from the external outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mindfulness: Observing the Transient Nature of Longing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mindfulness, deeply rooted in Buddhist traditions, emphasizes cultivating &lt;strong&gt;present moment awareness without judgment&lt;/strong&gt;. When it comes to desires, mindfulness encourages us to observe them as transient mental events, rather than immediately clinging to them or acting upon them. The problem isn’t the desire itself, but our &lt;strong&gt;attachment&lt;/strong&gt; to it and the mistaken belief that fulfilling every desire will lead to lasting happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider the &lt;strong&gt;wish for a specific career promotion&lt;/strong&gt;. You might spend countless hours dreaming about the new title, the higher salary, the perceived prestige.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attachment to Impermanence:&lt;/strong&gt; From a mindful perspective, even if you secure the promotion, the initial elation is fleeting. New stresses, greater responsibilities, or the realization that the role isn’t what you imagined often follow. Your happiness becomes dependent on an external condition, which is inherently unstable and subject to change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Suffering from Non-Attainment:&lt;/strong&gt; If the promotion doesn’t materialize, your intense wish and attachment can lead to profound disappointment, anger, or a sense of failure. Your mental peace is disrupted by clinging to a future scenario that didn’t unfold as desired.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Missing the Present:&lt;/strong&gt; While consumed by the longing for a future promotion, you might overlook the present value of your current work, the opportunities for learning and growth in your existing role, or the simple joys of your daily life. Your mind is constantly pulled away from the richness of the “now.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mindful approach would involve:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Observing the desire:&lt;/strong&gt; Noticing the wish for promotion as a thought or feeling, without getting swept away by it. “Ah, there’s the thought about wanting that promotion.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Non-attachment:&lt;/strong&gt; Working diligently towards your goals, but cultivating an acceptance of whatever outcome arises. Your inherent worth isn’t tied to the promotion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focus on the process:&lt;/strong&gt; Finding satisfaction in the effort, the learning, and the engagement with your current tasks, regardless of the future reward. Understanding that true contentment comes from within, not from external achievements, which are by nature impermanent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/be-careful-what-you-wish-for-timeless-wisdom/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The Unshakeable Truth? Embracing Justification&#39;s Limits in the Face of Münchhausen</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/unshakeable-truth-munchhausen-justification-limits/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Dive into the profound challenge of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M%C3%BCnchhausen_trilemma&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;the Münchhausen Trilemma&lt;/a&gt; and explore how we can find robust understanding even when faced with the limits of justification. This post unpacks the infinite regress, circular reasoning, and dogmatism, offering insights into practical ways to build knowledge and make decisions when absolute certainty remains elusive. Discover how embracing epistemological humility can lead to more resilient beliefs and a clearer path forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some clear, relatable examples for each part of the Münchhausen Trilemma:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An Endless Chain of Reasons (Infinite Regress):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Example: Imagine a child repeatedly asking “Why?” about everything.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Why is the sky blue?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Because of how light scatters in the atmosphere.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Why does light scatter like that?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Because of the wavelength of blue light and the size of air molecules.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Why do light and molecules behave that way?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;…and so on, potentially forever, without reaching an ultimate, self-evident first principle. Each answer requires another explanation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Circular Reasoning (Arguing in Circles):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Example: A classic example is the “Bible is true because it says it’s true, and it says it’s God’s word, so it must be true.”
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“How do you know the Bible is true?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Because the Bible says it’s the word of God, and God would not lie.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“How do you know God would not lie?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Because the Bible says God is truthful.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The justification for the Bible’s truth relies on the Bible’s truth itself, creating a closed loop without external validation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make Some Unproven Assumptions (Dogmatism):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Example: Someone firmly believing that all alternative medicine is inherently fraudulent, simply because they “know” that traditional medicine is the only valid form of healing, without having researched or considered any evidence for alternative practices.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“I refuse to even consider acupuncture; it’s just quackery.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“But have you seen any studies on its effectiveness for pain relief?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Doesn’t matter. It’s not ‘real’ medicine, and I don’t need evidence to know that.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This person stops the chain of justification by declaring a certain premise (only traditional medicine is valid) as a self-evident truth, not requiring any further proof or inquiry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, how do we operate in the face of these seemingly intractable challenges? The key lies not in overcoming the trilemma in an absolute sense, but in understanding its implications and adopting more pragmatic and resilient approaches to justification. For the infinite regress, we learn to accept “sufficient justification” for a given context, often relying on widely accepted scientific consensus, practical utility, or community agreement as a temporary bedrock. To counter circular reasoning, we must cultivate a rigorous commitment to external validation, constantly seeking independent evidence or different perspectives to break the self-referential loop. Finally, to avoid falling into dogmatism, we embrace intellectual humility, remaining open to new evidence, challenging our own assumptions, and critically evaluating the foundations of our beliefs, even those we hold dear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post boldly tackles the Münchhausen Trilemma, a foundational challenge to how we justify knowledge. We unpack its three inescapable paths: the infinite regress of reasons, the pitfalls of circular reasoning, and the rigid stance of dogmatism, illustrating each with clear, relatable examples. Rather than seeking an impossible absolute truth, the article proposes a practical framework for navigating these epistemological hurdles. It advocates for embracing “sufficient justification” within specific contexts, actively seeking external validation to break circular logic, and cultivating intellectual humility to guard against unproven assumptions. Ultimately, this piece empowers readers to build more resilient beliefs and make informed decisions by understanding and intelligently operating within the inherent limits of human justification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Links:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://philosophorsuni.substack.com/p/in-plain-english-munchhausen-trilemma&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;In Plain English: Münchhausen Trilemma&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thecollector.com/what-is-munchausen-trilemma/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;What Is Munchausen’s Trilemma?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jun 2025 13:18:57 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/unshakeable-truth-munchhausen-justification-limits/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The Spectrum of Motivation: Material and Non-Material Drivers</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/the-spectrum-of-motivation/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;What truly drives us to be productive? It’s rarely just about the paycheck. This diagram breaks down the core elements of motivation, revealing the spectrum from tangible rewards to intangible drivers that influence our engagement and output. Let’s explore the key categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.g.s4.mega.io/ckcmkjmaqedml3aiyva3m3o2rbwu4mbvztutq/poplauki/blog/the-spectrum-of-motivation.svg&quot; alt=&quot;The Spectrum of Motivation&quot; /&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 20:18:57 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/the-spectrum-of-motivation/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Stop Wishing, Start Doing: Stoic Quotes to Ignite Action and Focus</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/stop-wishing-start-doing-stoic/</link>
        <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t need more time, you need less distractions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t need motivation, you need self-control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t need more resources, you need resourcefulness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t need luck, you need preparation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t need to be busy, you need to be focused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t need to know everything, you just need to start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have everything you need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/stop-wishing-start-doing-stoic/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>How to Stop Comparing Yourself to Others and Find Your Own Path: Philosophical Reflections on the Meaning of Life</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/stop-comparing-find-your-path/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Comparing ourselves to others is a habit instilled in us from early childhood. We learn to see ourselves through the eyes of others, to be the object of someone’s assessment, to strive to meet external expectations. This is how a meaningless race begins, in which we lose ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it’s worth asking: is there a final goal in this race? Can we truly find fulfillment by trying to catch up to others’ successes, changing ourselves according to someone else’s standards?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are rarely taught to follow the path of our own soul, to seek the unique within ourselves, to be in agreement with ourselves. How often do we allow the external world to become our guide, forgetting that true freedom is not the right to be like everyone else, but the right to be oneself?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Victory can only be called genuine when it is the result of an internal choice, a response from the heart, a movement of our own will. Only by stepping beyond imposed stereotypes can we begin to live our real life, and not just play a social role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything else is just an attempt to stay afloat on the surface of familiar scenarios, never allowing ourselves the question: “Who am I, really?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to move closer to your essence, try taking a step:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Live from the inside out, not the outside in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allow yourself to be responsible for your feelings and decisions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give up comparison and competition—choose exploration and acceptance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t explain yourself to the world—the world needs your presence, not your report.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work thoughtfully, not by exhausting yourself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Awaken your creative power; allow it to lead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fill every action with meaning and attention.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allow yourself to create the meaning of your life—don’t look for a ready-made one, but give birth to your own.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 21:10:49 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/stop-comparing-find-your-path/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Implementing Web Speech API: Advanced Text-to-Speech with SpeechSynthesisUtterance in JavaScript</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/web-speech-api-text-to-speech-javascript/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This article details the process of converting text to speech using the &lt;code&gt;SpeechSynthesisUtterance&lt;/code&gt; API in JavaScript. This robust API provides granular control over the voice, pitch, and rate of synthesized speech, making it an optimal choice for developing accessible web applications and enhancing user engagement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction: Leveraging the Web Speech API for Text-to-Speech&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;SpeechSynthesisUtterance&lt;/code&gt; API serves as a fundamental component of the Web Speech API, designed to convert textual content into spoken audio within web applications. This API offers comprehensive control over the voice characteristics, including pitch and rate, enabling developers to create accessible and highly engaging user experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Core Functionality: Understanding &lt;code&gt;SpeechSynthesisUtterance&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;SpeechSynthesisUtterance&lt;/code&gt; object represents a speech request and is the primary interface for configuring synthesized speech. Its constructor accepts a string, which is the text to be spoken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-javascript&quot; tabindex=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; utterance &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;SpeechSynthesisUtterance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&#39;Text to be spoken.&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key properties of the &lt;code&gt;SpeechSynthesisUtterance&lt;/code&gt; object allow for granular control over the output:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;text&lt;/code&gt;: The string of text that the &lt;code&gt;SpeechSynthesisUtterance&lt;/code&gt; will synthesize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;lang:&lt;/code&gt; The language of the utterance, specified as a BCP 47 language tag (e.g., &lt;code&gt;en-US&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;es-ES&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;voice&lt;/code&gt;: A &lt;code&gt;SpeechSynthesisVoice&lt;/code&gt; object that defines the voice to be used. If not specified, the browser will use its default voice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;pitch&lt;/code&gt;: The pitch of the voice. A value between 0 (lowest) and 2 (highest), with 1 being the default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;rate&lt;/code&gt;: The speed at which the utterance is spoken. A value between 0.1 (slowest) and 10 (fastest), with 1 being the default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;volume&lt;/code&gt;: The volume of the utterance. A value between 0 (silent) and 1 (loudest), with 1 being the default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speech operations are managed by the window.speechSynthesis interface, which provides methods such as speak(), pause(), resume(), and cancel().&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Practical Implementation: Basic Text-to-Speech&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following example illustrates a basic implementation of the SpeechSynthesisUtterance API to synthesize the text ‘Hello, world!’ into spoken audio:
JavaScript&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-javascript&quot; tabindex=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; utterance &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;SpeechSynthesisUtterance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&#39;Hello, world!&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
utterance&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;pitch &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1.5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// Sets the pitch to 1.5 (range 0 to 2)&lt;/span&gt;
utterance&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;rate &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1.2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// Sets the speech rate to 1.2 (range 0.1 to 10)&lt;/span&gt;

window&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;speechSynthesis&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;speak&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;utterance&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For comprehensive documentation regarding the SpeechSynthesisUtterance API, consult the official MDN Web Docs: &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/SpeechSynthesis&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/SpeechSynthesis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Managing Voices: Asynchronous Loading and Selection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent Chrome versions, the window.speechSynthesis.getVoices() method may initially return an empty array upon page load. This behavior occurs because Chrome asynchronously fetches the list of available voices from its servers. To ensure voices are populated prior to text synthesis, it is imperative to implement a callback mechanism that awaits the completion of voice loading. The following code snippet demonstrates this approach:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-javascript&quot; tabindex=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;window&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;speechSynthesis&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function-variable function&quot;&gt;onvoiceschanged&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; voices &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; window&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;speechSynthesis&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;getVoices&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  console&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&#39;Available voices loaded:&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; voices&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// Example: Selecting a specific voice&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// const desiredVoice = voices.find(voice =&gt; voice.name === &#39;Google US English&#39;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// if (desiredVoice) {&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;//   utterance.voice = desiredVoice;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// }&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This code snippet utilizes the &lt;code&gt;onvoiceschanged&lt;/code&gt; event to ensure the &lt;code&gt;voices&lt;/code&gt; array is populated before attempting to access or select a specific voice for text-to-speech operations. The &lt;code&gt;voices&lt;/code&gt; array can then be iterated to identify and assign the desired voice to the &lt;code&gt;SpeechSynthesisUtterance&lt;/code&gt; instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Advanced Use Cases and Considerations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;SpeechSynthesisUtterance&lt;/code&gt; API facilitates a wide range of advanced web application features:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accessibility Enhancements:&lt;/strong&gt; The &lt;code&gt;SpeechSynthesisUtterance&lt;/code&gt; API can be leveraged to provide auditory feedback for user interactions, guiding users through intricate processes or conveying critical notifications, thereby enhancing accessibility for individuals with visual impairments or cognitive disabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interactive User Interfaces:&lt;/strong&gt; Implement voice-controlled interfaces, enabling users to navigate web pages, select options, and execute commands through spoken input, fostering a hands-free or alternative interaction paradigm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Educational Platform Integration:&lt;/strong&gt; Convert static, text-based educational content into dynamic audio lectures, thereby broadening accessibility and diversifying learning modalities for various demographics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personalized User Experiences:&lt;/strong&gt; Customize the vocal characteristics and stylistic attributes of the synthesized speech to align with specific brand identities or user preferences, thereby creating highly differentiated and engaging web applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Browser Compatibility and Asynchronous Voice Loading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;SpeechSynthesisUtterance&lt;/code&gt; API is widely supported across modern web browsers. Below is an overview of its compatibility status:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chrome: Fully supported from version 4 and up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Firefox: Fully supported from version 2 and up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Safari: Fully supported from version 3.1 and up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Edge: Fully supported from version 12 and up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opera: Fully supported from version 10 and up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note on Voice Consistency:&lt;/strong&gt; It is important for developers to be aware that the availability and quality of synthesized voices can vary significantly across different browsers and operating systems. This necessitates robust testing across target environments and potentially offering users a selection of available voices within the application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;SpeechSynthesisUtterance&lt;/code&gt; API provides a powerful and flexible mechanism for integrating text-to-speech capabilities into web applications. By mastering its core functionalities and understanding key considerations such as asynchronous voice loading, developers can create more accessible, interactive, and engaging user experiences. Its broad browser support further solidifies its position as a valuable tool in modern web development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Resources: Demos and Further Reading:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Live Demo:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://wirtaw.github.io/speech_synthesis/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;https://wirtaw.github.io/speech_synthesis/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MDN Web Speech API Synthesis Examples:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://mdn.github.io/dom-examples/web-speech-api/speak-easy-synthesis/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;https://mdn.github.io/dom-examples/web-speech-api/speak-easy-synthesis/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Smashing Magazine Article:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2017/02/experimenting-with-speechsynthesis/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2017/02/experimenting-with-speechsynthesis/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GitHub Repository Example:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Drunkula/twitchtoolsglitch&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;github.com/Drunkula/twitchtoolsglitch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/web-speech-api-text-to-speech-javascript/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The Difference Between Being Alone and Loneliness</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/the-difference-between-being-alone-and-loneliness/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Social isolation can affect your mental health if you are not used to spending time with yourself. However, even this can be adapted to and enjoyed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many thinkers over the centuries have emphasized the importance of coming to terms with this state. Michel de Montaigne once even wrote: “The greatest thing in the world is to know how to belong to yourself.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solitude encourages the imagination and makes it possible for serious thoughts to appear in people’s heads that go beyond the usual routine and force the convolutions to move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Loneliness, on the other hand, is a negative experience. Self-pity, thoughts of a wasted life, sadness torment. And if you are really interested in your self-development, then it does not hurt to turn this feeling into positive and constructive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step to being happy alone with yourself is accepting the situation. You need to ask yourself questions, turning loneliness into a constructive pastime: what do I really value in life? What do I need most? What do I need to do with…? What’s next?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second step is to keep your mind and body in constant tone. You need your body to calm your brain. You need feelings to organize your thoughts. Do not feed yourself with empty chatter and empty dramatic thoughts that only worsen the situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t have to run from anything. Instead of running away from what is, you should notice what is right under your nose. It sounds a bit complicated, but think about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try starting a journal and writing down thoughts about what interests you. Write poetry. Download Duolingo and delve into some new language. Start writing your autobiography or a book. Visit a virtual museum. Learn something new through YouTube or take a course that will help accelerate your career growth and expand your competence. Anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being happy alone with yourself is a constant striving to be better mentally, socially and emotionally for yourself and your loved ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today’s topic is a bit complicated, but relevant - no offense. And we will end it with a wise saying: “You cannot be lonely if you like the person you are alone with.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 20:44:16 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/the-difference-between-being-alone-and-loneliness/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Finding Inner Peace in a Crazy World</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/finding-inner-peace-crazy-world/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One day you stop fussing and trying to prove something to someone, you look with a smile at the world around you with all its madness, you don’t rush to please people, you don’t rush to give advice or judge or save anyone, you stop answering calls from people who haven’t admired or interested you for a long time, you look at the sky more than at who is busy with what and how they live, you remember what inspires you regardless of the circumstances, you don’t apologize, you don’t explain, you don’t argue, you don’t waste time on the uninteresting and temporary, and you discover incredible peace and many things that you didn’t notice before in the pursuit of meeting someone’s ideas or meeting someone’s expectations.  Comfort within is more precious than any temptations of temporary pleasure. More precious than any temporary people and temporary things. Everything you like is personal, and the personal belongs only to the person you see in the mirror. The rest is empty speculation and conjecture of those who are trying to see something else in you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are your own best ally in how to be yourself and be happy in this crazy world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;em&gt;Tatiana Marach&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/finding-inner-peace-crazy-world/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Stop Doing This: Habits That Kill Success</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/habits-that-kill-success/</link>
        <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop being a people-pleaser. It’s impossible to please everyone, and it’s stressful. It’s better to have a small circle of close contacts than many acquaintances you need to appease. You want to be successful, not a sycophant, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop hanging out with nasty people. Your environment either pulls you up or tramples you further into the ground. Choose who to be friends with and who to surround yourself with practically. Avoid garbage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop watching porn so often (men). Not only is it addictive, but with each orgasm, you lose strength - you ejaculate not only semen but also your motivation. It’s better to save energy and spend your time more wisely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop needing to talk when you’re bored. Don’t know what to do? Don’t call someone for the sake of hour-long conversations about nothing. Instead, read/listen to a book or do something you’ve been putting off for days. Get rid of the need to fill the silence with empty chatter. Fill it with your own depth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop caring about the opinions of others. It’s beyond your control. And if you can’t control it, why worry and fret? It’s a waste of time. Be independent and free yourself from the shackles of approval - they hinder your path to success. Not all your actions will be approved by others, so boldly ignore them. Approve of yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop being in destructive relationships. Does your partner constantly pressure you? Constantly provoke quarrels and scandals? Is there no constructiveness in the relationship? Don’t hope for the best; move on. Break up. Spare your nerves; you’ll need them later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop relying on miracles or luck. 99% of all results depend on your efforts, perseverance, and ambitions. Why would you rot in the shadows for 60 years, hoping for a miracle, if you can create that miracle yourself in a shorter time?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop procrastinating. If you need to do something, do it. Don’t think that tomorrow you’ll find a compromise with yourself and want to do something worthwhile. Do what’s necessary immediately. Don’t deceive yourself, and don’t put obligations in the back burner. By doing this, you’re only delaying your success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 21 Dec 2024 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/habits-that-kill-success/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>4 foundations for self-discipline</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/four-foundations-of-self-discipline/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;1. Too many responsibilities - a destructive break to pieces. Do only what you want to do no matter what. Ignore the irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each commitment that you shoulder affects willpower.
If there is too much excess, it will not stand and you will break.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. Start the day with the most important thing. Something meaningful can be done in the first hour after waking up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don’t want to load yourself with something significant early, do something small. It’s better than just sticking to the phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3. Be sharp and serious about yourself. If you forgot to do something, do not wish yourself, but punish yourself for the offense.
Not with a whip, of course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sacrifice sleep to complete what was promised, for example. So the burden is off your shoulders, and self-confidence increases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4. Routine correction. Plan as much as possible. Stick to the schedule until the very end of the day, do not shirk. When planning, you must take into account your priorities and adhere to their implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more habits and rules you introduce into your routine, the less you have to strain to maintain self-discipline. It will become the same effort as going to the toilet - by default, successful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A strong and reasonable schedule is a must-have for outstanding people. Sooner or later, you still have to take control of the days. And it is better if you come to this yourself, and not forced by circumstances. There will be experience.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2024 08:18:57 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/four-foundations-of-self-discipline/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Self-restraint and sacrifice</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/self-resistaint-and-sacrifice/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It may be that the taste for self-restraint which these creeds, however false, have instilled in mankind has been of some use in strengthening the human race.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the strength of the generic and individual character consists chiefly in the capacity to sacrifice the present to the future, to scorn the temptations of an ephemeral pleasure for a more distant and lasting satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more this faculty is exercised, the more exalted and strong becomes the character; and the highest heroism is attained by those who, in order to preserve or win liberty and truth for other, perhaps distant, ages, renounce the pleasures of life, and even life itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;© James George Frazer
“The Golden Bough”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2024 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/self-resistaint-and-sacrifice/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Success Piramida</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/success-pyramide/</link>
        <description></description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2024 08:18:57 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/success-pyramide/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>
