<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:base="https://wirtaw.github.io/blog" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Poplavskij Vladimir blog</title>
    <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/feed.xml</link>
    <atom:link href="https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <description>English</description>
    <language>en</language>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The Double-Edged Sword of Desire: Why &quot;Be Careful What You Wish For&quot; is Timeless Wisdom</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/be-careful-what-you-wish-for-timeless-wisdom/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“That’s a big takeaway from history, and it leads to a realization that will always be true: Be careful what you wish for.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;– “Same as Ever: A Guide to What Never Changes” &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Morgan-Housel/e/B084ZNV1LR&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;Morgan Housel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This powerful quote distills a truth as old as humanity itself. We often chase desires with unwavering focus, convinced that their attainment will bring ultimate happiness. Yet, history, personal experience, and profound philosophical traditions consistently reveal a paradox: getting exactly what we want can sometimes lead to unforeseen difficulties, deeper dissatisfaction, or even regret. Both Stoicism and Mindfulness offer invaluable frameworks for understanding this intricate relationship with our desires, guiding us toward a more discerning and peaceful approach to life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stoicism: Mastering the Inner Citadel Against External Desires&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stoicism, an ancient philosophy focused on virtue, reason, and living in harmony with nature, provides a robust framework for understanding the pitfalls of unexamined desires. Its core principle, the &lt;strong&gt;Dichotomy of Control&lt;/strong&gt;, teaches us to distinguish between what is within our power (our thoughts, judgments, and actions) and what is not (external events, other people’s opinions, health, wealth). Wishing excessively for things outside our control is, to a Stoic, a direct path to suffering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, consider the &lt;strong&gt;desire for fame or public recognition&lt;/strong&gt;. You might pour your energy into a creative project, dreaming of accolades and widespread appreciation. A Stoic would caution against this fervent wish. Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;External Dependency:&lt;/strong&gt; Fame is an external “indifferent.” It’s not inherently good or bad, and crucially, it’s not something you can control. You can create the art, but you can’t control how others react to it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vulnerability to Fortune:&lt;/strong&gt; If your peace of mind hinges on public approval, you become enslaved to the fickle whims of others. What if the project flops? What if success brings unwanted scrutiny or pressure? Seneca, a prominent Stoic, warned extensively about the dangers of seeking popularity, as it often compromises one’s integrity and inner peace.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compromising Virtue:&lt;/strong&gt; The intense longing for external validation can subtly erode your commitment to virtue. You might find yourself making choices based on what’s popular rather than what’s right or authentic to your craft.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of wishing for fame, a Stoic would advise internalizing your desires: wish to &lt;strong&gt;produce your best work&lt;/strong&gt;, to &lt;strong&gt;act with integrity&lt;/strong&gt;, and to &lt;strong&gt;apply yourself diligently&lt;/strong&gt;. True satisfaction comes from the virtuous effort itself, not from the external outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mindfulness: Observing the Transient Nature of Longing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mindfulness, deeply rooted in Buddhist traditions, emphasizes cultivating &lt;strong&gt;present moment awareness without judgment&lt;/strong&gt;. When it comes to desires, mindfulness encourages us to observe them as transient mental events, rather than immediately clinging to them or acting upon them. The problem isn’t the desire itself, but our &lt;strong&gt;attachment&lt;/strong&gt; to it and the mistaken belief that fulfilling every desire will lead to lasting happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider the &lt;strong&gt;wish for a specific career promotion&lt;/strong&gt;. You might spend countless hours dreaming about the new title, the higher salary, the perceived prestige.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attachment to Impermanence:&lt;/strong&gt; From a mindful perspective, even if you secure the promotion, the initial elation is fleeting. New stresses, greater responsibilities, or the realization that the role isn’t what you imagined often follow. Your happiness becomes dependent on an external condition, which is inherently unstable and subject to change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Suffering from Non-Attainment:&lt;/strong&gt; If the promotion doesn’t materialize, your intense wish and attachment can lead to profound disappointment, anger, or a sense of failure. Your mental peace is disrupted by clinging to a future scenario that didn’t unfold as desired.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Missing the Present:&lt;/strong&gt; While consumed by the longing for a future promotion, you might overlook the present value of your current work, the opportunities for learning and growth in your existing role, or the simple joys of your daily life. Your mind is constantly pulled away from the richness of the “now.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mindful approach would involve:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Observing the desire:&lt;/strong&gt; Noticing the wish for promotion as a thought or feeling, without getting swept away by it. “Ah, there’s the thought about wanting that promotion.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Non-attachment:&lt;/strong&gt; Working diligently towards your goals, but cultivating an acceptance of whatever outcome arises. Your inherent worth isn’t tied to the promotion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focus on the process:&lt;/strong&gt; Finding satisfaction in the effort, the learning, and the engagement with your current tasks, regardless of the future reward. Understanding that true contentment comes from within, not from external achievements, which are by nature impermanent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/be-careful-what-you-wish-for-timeless-wisdom/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The Unshakeable Truth? Embracing Justification&#39;s Limits in the Face of Münchhausen</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/unshakeable-truth-munchhausen-justification-limits/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Dive into the profound challenge of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M%C3%BCnchhausen_trilemma&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;the Münchhausen Trilemma&lt;/a&gt; and explore how we can find robust understanding even when faced with the limits of justification. This post unpacks the infinite regress, circular reasoning, and dogmatism, offering insights into practical ways to build knowledge and make decisions when absolute certainty remains elusive. Discover how embracing epistemological humility can lead to more resilient beliefs and a clearer path forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some clear, relatable examples for each part of the Münchhausen Trilemma:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An Endless Chain of Reasons (Infinite Regress):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Example: Imagine a child repeatedly asking “Why?” about everything.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Why is the sky blue?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Because of how light scatters in the atmosphere.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Why does light scatter like that?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Because of the wavelength of blue light and the size of air molecules.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Why do light and molecules behave that way?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;…and so on, potentially forever, without reaching an ultimate, self-evident first principle. Each answer requires another explanation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Circular Reasoning (Arguing in Circles):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Example: A classic example is the “Bible is true because it says it’s true, and it says it’s God’s word, so it must be true.”
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“How do you know the Bible is true?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Because the Bible says it’s the word of God, and God would not lie.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“How do you know God would not lie?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Because the Bible says God is truthful.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The justification for the Bible’s truth relies on the Bible’s truth itself, creating a closed loop without external validation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make Some Unproven Assumptions (Dogmatism):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Example: Someone firmly believing that all alternative medicine is inherently fraudulent, simply because they “know” that traditional medicine is the only valid form of healing, without having researched or considered any evidence for alternative practices.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“I refuse to even consider acupuncture; it’s just quackery.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“But have you seen any studies on its effectiveness for pain relief?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Doesn’t matter. It’s not ‘real’ medicine, and I don’t need evidence to know that.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This person stops the chain of justification by declaring a certain premise (only traditional medicine is valid) as a self-evident truth, not requiring any further proof or inquiry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, how do we operate in the face of these seemingly intractable challenges? The key lies not in overcoming the trilemma in an absolute sense, but in understanding its implications and adopting more pragmatic and resilient approaches to justification. For the infinite regress, we learn to accept “sufficient justification” for a given context, often relying on widely accepted scientific consensus, practical utility, or community agreement as a temporary bedrock. To counter circular reasoning, we must cultivate a rigorous commitment to external validation, constantly seeking independent evidence or different perspectives to break the self-referential loop. Finally, to avoid falling into dogmatism, we embrace intellectual humility, remaining open to new evidence, challenging our own assumptions, and critically evaluating the foundations of our beliefs, even those we hold dear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post boldly tackles the Münchhausen Trilemma, a foundational challenge to how we justify knowledge. We unpack its three inescapable paths: the infinite regress of reasons, the pitfalls of circular reasoning, and the rigid stance of dogmatism, illustrating each with clear, relatable examples. Rather than seeking an impossible absolute truth, the article proposes a practical framework for navigating these epistemological hurdles. It advocates for embracing “sufficient justification” within specific contexts, actively seeking external validation to break circular logic, and cultivating intellectual humility to guard against unproven assumptions. Ultimately, this piece empowers readers to build more resilient beliefs and make informed decisions by understanding and intelligently operating within the inherent limits of human justification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Links:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://philosophorsuni.substack.com/p/in-plain-english-munchhausen-trilemma&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;In Plain English: Münchhausen Trilemma&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thecollector.com/what-is-munchausen-trilemma/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;What Is Munchausen’s Trilemma?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jun 2025 13:18:57 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/unshakeable-truth-munchhausen-justification-limits/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The Spectrum of Motivation: Material and Non-Material Drivers</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/the-spectrum-of-motivation/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;What truly drives us to be productive? It’s rarely just about the paycheck. This diagram breaks down the core elements of motivation, revealing the spectrum from tangible rewards to intangible drivers that influence our engagement and output. Let’s explore the key categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;svg width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;auto&quot; viewBox=&quot;0.00 0.00 1189.42 548.00&quot; xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; xmlns:xlink=&quot;http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink&quot;&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;graph0&quot; class=&quot;graph&quot; transform=&quot;scale(1 1) rotate(0) translate(4 544)&quot;&gt;&lt;polygon fill=&quot;white&quot; stroke=&quot;none&quot; points=&quot;-4,4 -4,-544 1185.42,-544 1185.42,4 -4,4&quot;&gt;&lt;/polygon&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;node1&quot; class=&quot;node&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        A      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;ellipse fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; cx=&quot;519.13&quot; cy=&quot;-522&quot; rx=&quot;69.78&quot; ry=&quot;18&quot;&gt;&lt;/ellipse&gt;&lt;text text-anchor=&quot;middle&quot; x=&quot;519.13&quot; y=&quot;-516.95&quot; font-family=&quot;Times,serif&quot; font-size=&quot;14.00&quot;&gt;        Needs, interests      &lt;/text&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;node2&quot; class=&quot;node&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        B      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;ellipse fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; cx=&quot;386.13&quot; cy=&quot;-450&quot; rx=&quot;115.33&quot; ry=&quot;18&quot;&gt;&lt;/ellipse&gt;&lt;text text-anchor=&quot;middle&quot; x=&quot;386.13&quot; y=&quot;-444.95&quot; font-family=&quot;Times,serif&quot; font-size=&quot;14.00&quot;&gt;        Material needs and interests      &lt;/text&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;edge1&quot; class=&quot;edge&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        A-&amp;gt;B      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;path fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; d=&quot;M489.28,-505.29C471.15,-495.75 447.73,-483.42 427.8,-472.93&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;polygon fill=&quot;black&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; points=&quot;429.55,-469.9 419.07,-468.34 426.29,-476.09 429.55,-469.9&quot;&gt;&lt;/polygon&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;node3&quot; class=&quot;node&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        C      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;ellipse fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; cx=&quot;653.13&quot; cy=&quot;-450&quot; rx=&quot;133.24&quot; ry=&quot;18&quot;&gt;&lt;/ellipse&gt;&lt;text text-anchor=&quot;middle&quot; x=&quot;653.13&quot; y=&quot;-444.95&quot; font-family=&quot;Times,serif&quot; font-size=&quot;14.00&quot;&gt;        Non-material needs and interests      &lt;/text&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;edge2&quot; class=&quot;edge&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        A-&amp;gt;C      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;path fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; d=&quot;M549.2,-505.29C567.34,-495.82 590.72,-483.6 610.72,-473.16&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;polygon fill=&quot;black&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; points=&quot;612.23,-476.31 619.48,-468.58 608.99,-470.11 612.23,-476.31&quot;&gt;&lt;/polygon&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;node4&quot; class=&quot;node&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        D      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;ellipse fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; cx=&quot;386.13&quot; cy=&quot;-378&quot; rx=&quot;85.64&quot; ry=&quot;18&quot;&gt;&lt;/ellipse&gt;&lt;text text-anchor=&quot;middle&quot; x=&quot;386.13&quot; y=&quot;-372.95&quot; font-family=&quot;Times,serif&quot; font-size=&quot;14.00&quot;&gt;        Material motivation      &lt;/text&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;edge3&quot; class=&quot;edge&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        B-&amp;gt;D      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;path fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; d=&quot;M386.13,-431.7C386.13,-424.41 386.13,-415.73 386.13,-407.54&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;polygon fill=&quot;black&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; points=&quot;389.63,-407.62 386.13,-397.62 382.63,-407.62 389.63,-407.62&quot;&gt;&lt;/polygon&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;node5&quot; class=&quot;node&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        E      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;ellipse fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; cx=&quot;653.13&quot; cy=&quot;-378&quot; rx=&quot;103.56&quot; ry=&quot;18&quot;&gt;&lt;/ellipse&gt;&lt;text text-anchor=&quot;middle&quot; x=&quot;653.13&quot; y=&quot;-372.95&quot; font-family=&quot;Times,serif&quot; font-size=&quot;14.00&quot;&gt;        Non-material motivation      &lt;/text&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;edge4&quot; class=&quot;edge&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        C-&amp;gt;E      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;path fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; d=&quot;M653.13,-431.7C653.13,-424.41 653.13,-415.73 653.13,-407.54&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;polygon fill=&quot;black&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; points=&quot;656.63,-407.62 653.13,-397.62 649.63,-407.62 656.63,-407.62&quot;&gt;&lt;/polygon&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;node6&quot; class=&quot;node&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        F      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;ellipse fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; cx=&quot;85.13&quot; cy=&quot;-162&quot; rx=&quot;85.13&quot; ry=&quot;18&quot;&gt;&lt;/ellipse&gt;&lt;text text-anchor=&quot;middle&quot; x=&quot;85.13&quot; y=&quot;-156.95&quot; font-family=&quot;Times,serif&quot; font-size=&quot;14.00&quot;&gt;        Creative motivation      &lt;/text&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;edge5&quot; class=&quot;edge&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        D-&amp;gt;F      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;path fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; d=&quot;M360,-360.39C344.02,-350.12 323.23,-336.53 305.13,-324 236.76,-276.66 158.6,-218.46 116.3,-186.61&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;polygon fill=&quot;black&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; points=&quot;118.64,-183.99 108.55,-180.76 114.42,-189.57 118.64,-183.99&quot;&gt;&lt;/polygon&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;node7&quot; class=&quot;node&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        G      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;ellipse fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; cx=&quot;397.13&quot; cy=&quot;-306&quot; rx=&quot;83.08&quot; ry=&quot;18&quot;&gt;&lt;/ellipse&gt;&lt;text text-anchor=&quot;middle&quot; x=&quot;397.13&quot; y=&quot;-300.95&quot; font-family=&quot;Times,serif&quot; font-size=&quot;14.00&quot;&gt;        Rent from property      &lt;/text&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;edge6&quot; class=&quot;edge&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        D-&amp;gt;G      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;path fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; d=&quot;M388.85,-359.7C390.01,-352.32 391.39,-343.52 392.69,-335.25&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;polygon fill=&quot;black&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; points=&quot;396.11,-336.02 394.21,-325.6 389.2,-334.93 396.11,-336.02&quot;&gt;&lt;/polygon&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;node8&quot; class=&quot;node&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        H      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;ellipse fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; cx=&quot;642.13&quot; cy=&quot;-306&quot; rx=&quot;69.26&quot; ry=&quot;18&quot;&gt;&lt;/ellipse&gt;&lt;text text-anchor=&quot;middle&quot; x=&quot;642.13&quot; y=&quot;-300.95&quot; font-family=&quot;Times,serif&quot; font-size=&quot;14.00&quot;&gt;        Meaning of life      &lt;/text&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;edge7&quot; class=&quot;edge&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        E-&amp;gt;H      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;path fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; d=&quot;M650.41,-359.7C649.25,-352.32 647.87,-343.52 646.57,-335.25&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;polygon fill=&quot;black&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; points=&quot;650.06,-334.93 645.05,-325.6 643.15,-336.02 650.06,-334.93&quot;&gt;&lt;/polygon&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;node9&quot; class=&quot;node&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        I      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;ellipse fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; cx=&quot;861.13&quot; cy=&quot;-306&quot; rx=&quot;132.22&quot; ry=&quot;18&quot;&gt;&lt;/ellipse&gt;&lt;text text-anchor=&quot;middle&quot; x=&quot;861.13&quot; y=&quot;-300.95&quot; font-family=&quot;Times,serif&quot; font-size=&quot;14.00&quot;&gt;        Social standing, status in society      &lt;/text&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;edge8&quot; class=&quot;edge&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        E-&amp;gt;I      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;path fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; d=&quot;M699.29,-361.46C729.62,-351.26 769.56,-337.82 802.17,-326.84&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;polygon fill=&quot;black&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; points=&quot;803.13,-330.21 811.49,-323.7 800.9,-323.58 803.13,-330.21&quot;&gt;&lt;/polygon&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;node10&quot; class=&quot;node&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        J      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;ellipse fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; cx=&quot;273.13&quot; cy=&quot;-90&quot; rx=&quot;95.37&quot; ry=&quot;18&quot;&gt;&lt;/ellipse&gt;&lt;text text-anchor=&quot;middle&quot; x=&quot;273.13&quot; y=&quot;-84.95&quot; font-family=&quot;Times,serif&quot; font-size=&quot;14.00&quot;&gt;        Remuneration of labor      &lt;/text&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;edge9&quot; class=&quot;edge&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        F-&amp;gt;J      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;path fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; d=&quot;M125.92,-145.81C153.72,-135.46 190.77,-121.67 220.75,-110.5&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;polygon fill=&quot;black&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; points=&quot;221.87,-113.82 230.02,-107.05 219.43,-107.26 221.87,-113.82&quot;&gt;&lt;/polygon&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;node11&quot; class=&quot;node&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        K      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;ellipse fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; cx=&quot;397.13&quot; cy=&quot;-234&quot; rx=&quot;83.08&quot; ry=&quot;18&quot;&gt;&lt;/ellipse&gt;&lt;text text-anchor=&quot;middle&quot; x=&quot;397.13&quot; y=&quot;-228.95&quot; font-family=&quot;Times,serif&quot; font-size=&quot;14.00&quot;&gt;        Rent from property      &lt;/text&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;edge10&quot; class=&quot;edge&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        G-&amp;gt;K      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;path fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; d=&quot;M397.13,-287.7C397.13,-280.41 397.13,-271.73 397.13,-263.54&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;polygon fill=&quot;black&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; points=&quot;400.63,-263.62 397.13,-253.62 393.63,-263.62 400.63,-263.62&quot;&gt;&lt;/polygon&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;node12&quot; class=&quot;node&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        L      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;ellipse fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; cx=&quot;645.13&quot; cy=&quot;-234&quot; rx=&quot;116.35&quot; ry=&quot;18&quot;&gt;&lt;/ellipse&gt;&lt;text text-anchor=&quot;middle&quot; x=&quot;645.13&quot; y=&quot;-228.95&quot; font-family=&quot;Times,serif&quot; font-size=&quot;14.00&quot;&gt;        Evaluation of personal labor      &lt;/text&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;edge11&quot; class=&quot;edge&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        H-&amp;gt;L      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;path fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; d=&quot;M642.87,-287.7C643.18,-280.41 643.56,-271.73 643.91,-263.54&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;polygon fill=&quot;black&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; points=&quot;647.4,-263.76 644.33,-253.62 640.41,-263.46 647.4,-263.76&quot;&gt;&lt;/polygon&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;node13&quot; class=&quot;node&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        M      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;ellipse fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; cx=&quot;858.13&quot; cy=&quot;-234&quot; rx=&quot;72.34&quot; ry=&quot;18&quot;&gt;&lt;/ellipse&gt;&lt;text text-anchor=&quot;middle&quot; x=&quot;858.13&quot; y=&quot;-228.95&quot; font-family=&quot;Times,serif&quot; font-size=&quot;14.00&quot;&gt;        Prestige of labor      &lt;/text&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;edge12&quot; class=&quot;edge&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        I-&amp;gt;M      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;path fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; d=&quot;M860.39,-287.7C860.08,-280.41 859.7,-271.73 859.35,-263.54&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;polygon fill=&quot;black&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; points=&quot;862.85,-263.46 858.93,-253.62 855.86,-263.76 862.85,-263.46&quot;&gt;&lt;/polygon&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;node14&quot; class=&quot;node&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        N      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;ellipse fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; cx=&quot;273.13&quot; cy=&quot;-18&quot; rx=&quot;223.83&quot; ry=&quot;18&quot;&gt;&lt;/ellipse&gt;&lt;text text-anchor=&quot;middle&quot; x=&quot;273.13&quot; y=&quot;-12.95&quot; font-family=&quot;Times,serif&quot; font-size=&quot;14.00&quot;&gt;        Physical life, reproduction, comfort, safety, development      &lt;/text&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;edge13&quot; class=&quot;edge&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        J-&amp;gt;N      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;path fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; d=&quot;M267.22,-71.7C266.46,-64.41 266.22,-55.73 266.48,-47.54&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;polygon fill=&quot;black&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; points=&quot;269.97,-47.82 267.14,-37.61 262.99,-47.36 269.97,-47.82&quot;&gt;&lt;/polygon&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;node15&quot; class=&quot;node&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        O      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;ellipse fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; cx=&quot;412.13&quot; cy=&quot;-162&quot; rx=&quot;223.83&quot; ry=&quot;18&quot;&gt;&lt;/ellipse&gt;&lt;text text-anchor=&quot;middle&quot; x=&quot;412.13&quot; y=&quot;-156.95&quot; font-family=&quot;Times,serif&quot; font-size=&quot;14.00&quot;&gt;        Physical life, reproduction, comfort, safety, development      &lt;/text&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;edge14&quot; class=&quot;edge&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        K-&amp;gt;O      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;path fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; d=&quot;M400.84,-215.7C402.42,-208.32 404.3,-199.52 406.08,-191.25&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;polygon fill=&quot;black&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; points=&quot;409.48,-192.1 408.15,-181.58 402.63,-190.63 409.48,-192.1&quot;&gt;&lt;/polygon&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;node16&quot; class=&quot;node&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        P      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;ellipse fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; cx=&quot;843.13&quot; cy=&quot;-162&quot; rx=&quot;159.34&quot; ry=&quot;18&quot;&gt;&lt;/ellipse&gt;&lt;text text-anchor=&quot;middle&quot; x=&quot;843.13&quot; y=&quot;-156.95&quot; font-family=&quot;Times,serif&quot; font-size=&quot;14.00&quot;&gt;        Social (non-material) incentive package      &lt;/text&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;edge15&quot; class=&quot;edge&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        L-&amp;gt;P      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;path fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; d=&quot;M690.06,-217.12C718.33,-207.12 755.09,-194.13 785.5,-183.37&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;polygon fill=&quot;black&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; points=&quot;786.28,-186.81 794.54,-180.18 783.94,-180.21 786.28,-186.81&quot;&gt;&lt;/polygon&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;edge16&quot; class=&quot;edge&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        M-&amp;gt;P      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;path fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; d=&quot;M854.42,-215.7C852.84,-208.32 850.96,-199.52 849.18,-191.25&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;polygon fill=&quot;black&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; points=&quot;852.63,-190.63 847.11,-181.58 845.79,-192.1 852.63,-190.63&quot;&gt;&lt;/polygon&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;edge17&quot; class=&quot;edge&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        N-&amp;gt;J      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;path fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; d=&quot;M279.03,-36.1C279.79,-43.37 280.04,-52.04 279.78,-60.24&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;polygon fill=&quot;black&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; points=&quot;276.29,-59.98 279.14,-70.19 283.28,-60.43 276.29,-59.98&quot;&gt;&lt;/polygon&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;edge18&quot; class=&quot;edge&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        O-&amp;gt;J      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;path fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; d=&quot;M378.13,-143.88C359.24,-134.36 335.56,-122.44 315.48,-112.33&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;polygon fill=&quot;black&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; points=&quot;317.21,-109.28 306.7,-107.91 314.06,-115.53 317.21,-109.28&quot;&gt;&lt;/polygon&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;node17&quot; class=&quot;node&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        Q      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;ellipse fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; cx=&quot;599.13&quot; cy=&quot;-90&quot; rx=&quot;163.44&quot; ry=&quot;18&quot;&gt;&lt;/ellipse&gt;&lt;text text-anchor=&quot;middle&quot; x=&quot;599.13&quot; y=&quot;-84.95&quot; font-family=&quot;Times,serif&quot; font-size=&quot;14.00&quot;&gt;        Traditions, culture, civilizational identity      &lt;/text&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;edge19&quot; class=&quot;edge&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        P-&amp;gt;Q      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;path fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; d=&quot;M786.54,-144.76C750.79,-134.51 704.4,-121.2 666.72,-110.39&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;polygon fill=&quot;black&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; points=&quot;667.87,-107.08 657.29,-107.69 665.94,-113.81 667.87,-107.08&quot;&gt;&lt;/polygon&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;node18&quot; class=&quot;node&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        R      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;ellipse fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; cx=&quot;981.13&quot; cy=&quot;-90&quot; rx=&quot;200.29&quot; ry=&quot;18&quot;&gt;&lt;/ellipse&gt;&lt;text text-anchor=&quot;middle&quot; x=&quot;981.13&quot; y=&quot;-84.95&quot; font-family=&quot;Times,serif&quot; font-size=&quot;14.00&quot;&gt;        Social value scales formed by society and the state      &lt;/text&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g id=&quot;edge20&quot; class=&quot;edge&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;        P-&amp;gt;R      &lt;/title&gt;&lt;path fill=&quot;none&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; d=&quot;M876.54,-144.05C894.79,-134.79 917.63,-123.21 937.3,-113.23&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;polygon fill=&quot;black&quot; stroke=&quot;black&quot; points=&quot;938.87,-116.36 946.2,-108.72 935.7,-110.12 938.87,-116.36&quot;&gt;&lt;/polygon&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 20:18:57 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/the-spectrum-of-motivation/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Stop Wishing, Start Doing: Stoic Quotes to Ignite Action and Focus</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/stop-wishing-start-doing-stoic/</link>
        <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t need more time, you need less distractions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t need motivation, you need self-control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t need more resources, you need resourcefulness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t need luck, you need preparation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t need to be busy, you need to be focused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t need to know everything, you just need to start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have everything you need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/stop-wishing-start-doing-stoic/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The Difference Between Being Alone and Loneliness</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/the-difference-between-being-alone-and-loneliness/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Social isolation can affect your mental health if you are not used to spending time with yourself. However, even this can be adapted to and enjoyed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many thinkers over the centuries have emphasized the importance of coming to terms with this state. Michel de Montaigne once even wrote: “The greatest thing in the world is to know how to belong to yourself.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solitude encourages the imagination and makes it possible for serious thoughts to appear in people’s heads that go beyond the usual routine and force the convolutions to move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Loneliness, on the other hand, is a negative experience. Self-pity, thoughts of a wasted life, sadness torment. And if you are really interested in your self-development, then it does not hurt to turn this feeling into positive and constructive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step to being happy alone with yourself is accepting the situation. You need to ask yourself questions, turning loneliness into a constructive pastime: what do I really value in life? What do I need most? What do I need to do with…? What’s next?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second step is to keep your mind and body in constant tone. You need your body to calm your brain. You need feelings to organize your thoughts. Do not feed yourself with empty chatter and empty dramatic thoughts that only worsen the situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t have to run from anything. Instead of running away from what is, you should notice what is right under your nose. It sounds a bit complicated, but think about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try starting a journal and writing down thoughts about what interests you. Write poetry. Download Duolingo and delve into some new language. Start writing your autobiography or a book. Visit a virtual museum. Learn something new through YouTube or take a course that will help accelerate your career growth and expand your competence. Anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being happy alone with yourself is a constant striving to be better mentally, socially and emotionally for yourself and your loved ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today’s topic is a bit complicated, but relevant - no offense. And we will end it with a wise saying: “You cannot be lonely if you like the person you are alone with.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 20:44:16 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/the-difference-between-being-alone-and-loneliness/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Finding Inner Peace in a Crazy World</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/finding-inner-peace-crazy-world/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One day you stop fussing and trying to prove something to someone, you look with a smile at the world around you with all its madness, you don’t rush to please people, you don’t rush to give advice or judge or save anyone, you stop answering calls from people who haven’t admired or interested you for a long time, you look at the sky more than at who is busy with what and how they live, you remember what inspires you regardless of the circumstances, you don’t apologize, you don’t explain, you don’t argue, you don’t waste time on the uninteresting and temporary, and you discover incredible peace and many things that you didn’t notice before in the pursuit of meeting someone’s ideas or meeting someone’s expectations.  Comfort within is more precious than any temptations of temporary pleasure. More precious than any temporary people and temporary things. Everything you like is personal, and the personal belongs only to the person you see in the mirror. The rest is empty speculation and conjecture of those who are trying to see something else in you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are your own best ally in how to be yourself and be happy in this crazy world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;em&gt;Tatiana Marach&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/finding-inner-peace-crazy-world/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Stop Doing This: Habits That Kill Success</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/habits-that-kill-success/</link>
        <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop being a people-pleaser. It’s impossible to please everyone, and it’s stressful. It’s better to have a small circle of close contacts than many acquaintances you need to appease. You want to be successful, not a sycophant, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop hanging out with nasty people. Your environment either pulls you up or tramples you further into the ground. Choose who to be friends with and who to surround yourself with practically. Avoid garbage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop watching porn so often (men). Not only is it addictive, but with each orgasm, you lose strength - you ejaculate not only semen but also your motivation. It’s better to save energy and spend your time more wisely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop needing to talk when you’re bored. Don’t know what to do? Don’t call someone for the sake of hour-long conversations about nothing. Instead, read/listen to a book or do something you’ve been putting off for days. Get rid of the need to fill the silence with empty chatter. Fill it with your own depth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop caring about the opinions of others. It’s beyond your control. And if you can’t control it, why worry and fret? It’s a waste of time. Be independent and free yourself from the shackles of approval - they hinder your path to success. Not all your actions will be approved by others, so boldly ignore them. Approve of yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop being in destructive relationships. Does your partner constantly pressure you? Constantly provoke quarrels and scandals? Is there no constructiveness in the relationship? Don’t hope for the best; move on. Break up. Spare your nerves; you’ll need them later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop relying on miracles or luck. 99% of all results depend on your efforts, perseverance, and ambitions. Why would you rot in the shadows for 60 years, hoping for a miracle, if you can create that miracle yourself in a shorter time?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop procrastinating. If you need to do something, do it. Don’t think that tomorrow you’ll find a compromise with yourself and want to do something worthwhile. Do what’s necessary immediately. Don’t deceive yourself, and don’t put obligations in the back burner. By doing this, you’re only delaying your success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 21 Dec 2024 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/habits-that-kill-success/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>4 foundations for self-discipline</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/four-foundations-of-self-discipline/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;1. Too many responsibilities - a destructive break to pieces. Do only what you want to do no matter what. Ignore the irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each commitment that you shoulder affects willpower.
If there is too much excess, it will not stand and you will break.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. Start the day with the most important thing. Something meaningful can be done in the first hour after waking up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don’t want to load yourself with something significant early, do something small. It’s better than just sticking to the phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3. Be sharp and serious about yourself. If you forgot to do something, do not wish yourself, but punish yourself for the offense.
Not with a whip, of course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sacrifice sleep to complete what was promised, for example. So the burden is off your shoulders, and self-confidence increases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4. Routine correction. Plan as much as possible. Stick to the schedule until the very end of the day, do not shirk. When planning, you must take into account your priorities and adhere to their implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more habits and rules you introduce into your routine, the less you have to strain to maintain self-discipline. It will become the same effort as going to the toilet - by default, successful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A strong and reasonable schedule is a must-have for outstanding people. Sooner or later, you still have to take control of the days. And it is better if you come to this yourself, and not forced by circumstances. There will be experience.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2024 08:18:57 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/four-foundations-of-self-discipline/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Self-restraint and sacrifice</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/self-resistaint-and-sacrifice/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It may be that the taste for self-restraint which these creeds, however false, have instilled in mankind has been of some use in strengthening the human race.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the strength of the generic and individual character consists chiefly in the capacity to sacrifice the present to the future, to scorn the temptations of an ephemeral pleasure for a more distant and lasting satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more this faculty is exercised, the more exalted and strong becomes the character; and the highest heroism is attained by those who, in order to preserve or win liberty and truth for other, perhaps distant, ages, renounce the pleasures of life, and even life itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;© James George Frazer
“The Golden Bough”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2024 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/self-resistaint-and-sacrifice/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Success Piramida</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/success-pyramide/</link>
        <description></description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2024 08:18:57 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/success-pyramide/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>
