<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:base="https://wirtaw.github.io/blog" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Poplavskij Vladimir blog</title>
    <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/feed.xml</link>
    <atom:link href="https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <description>English</description>
    <language>en</language>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>4 foundations for self-discipline</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/four-foundations-of-self-discipline/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;1. Too many responsibilities - a destructive break to pieces. Do only what you want to do no matter what. Ignore the irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each commitment that you shoulder affects willpower.
If there is too much excess, it will not stand and you will break.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. Start the day with the most important thing. Something meaningful can be done in the first hour after waking up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don’t want to load yourself with something significant early, do something small. It&#39;s better than just sticking to the phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3. Be sharp and serious about yourself. If you forgot to do something, do not wish yourself, but punish yourself for the offense.
Not with a whip, of course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sacrifice sleep to complete what was promised, for example. So the burden is off your shoulders, and self-confidence increases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4. Routine correction. Plan as much as possible. Stick to the schedule until the very end of the day, do not shirk. When planning, you must take into account your priorities and adhere to their implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more habits and rules you introduce into your routine, the less you have to strain to maintain self-discipline. It will become the same effort as going to the toilet - by default, successful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A strong and reasonable schedule is a must-have for outstanding people. Sooner or later, you still have to take control of the days. And it is better if you come to this yourself, and not forced by circumstances. There will be experience.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2024 08:18:57 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/four-foundations-of-self-discipline/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Self-restraint and sacrifice</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/self-resistaint-and-sacrifice/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It may be that the taste for self-restraint which these creeds, however false, have instilled in mankind has been of some use in strengthening the human race.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the strength of the generic and individual character consists chiefly in the capacity to sacrifice the present to the future, to scorn the temptations of an ephemeral pleasure for a more distant and lasting satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more this faculty is exercised, the more exalted and strong becomes the character; and the highest heroism is attained by those who, in order to preserve or win liberty and truth for other, perhaps distant, ages, renounce the pleasures of life, and even life itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;© James George Frazer
&amp;quot;The Golden Bough&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2024 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/self-resistaint-and-sacrifice/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Success Piramida</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/success-pyramide/</link>
        <description></description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2024 08:18:57 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/success-pyramide/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>
