<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:base="https://wirtaw.github.io/blog" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Poplavskij Vladimir blog</title>
    <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/feed.xml</link>
    <atom:link href="https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <description>English</description>
    <language>en</language>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The Difference Between Being Alone and Loneliness</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/the-difference-between-being-alone-and-loneliness/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Social isolation can affect your mental health if you are not used to spending time with yourself. However, even this can be adapted to and enjoyed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many thinkers over the centuries have emphasized the importance of coming to terms with this state. Michel de Montaigne once even wrote: &amp;quot;The greatest thing in the world is to know how to belong to yourself.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solitude encourages the imagination and makes it possible for serious thoughts to appear in people&#39;s heads that go beyond the usual routine and force the convolutions to move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Loneliness, on the other hand, is a negative experience. Self-pity, thoughts of a wasted life, sadness torment. And if you are really interested in your self-development, then it does not hurt to turn this feeling into positive and constructive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step to being happy alone with yourself is accepting the situation. You need to ask yourself questions, turning loneliness into a constructive pastime: what do I really value in life? What do I need most? What do I need to do with...? What&#39;s next?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second step is to keep your mind and body in constant tone. You need your body to calm your brain. You need feelings to organize your thoughts. Do not feed yourself with empty chatter and empty dramatic thoughts that only worsen the situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don&#39;t have to run from anything. Instead of running away from what is, you should notice what is right under your nose. It sounds a bit complicated, but think about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try starting a journal and writing down thoughts about what interests you. Write poetry. Download Duolingo and delve into some new language. Start writing your autobiography or a book. Visit a virtual museum. Learn something new through YouTube or take a course that will help accelerate your career growth and expand your competence. Anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being happy alone with yourself is a constant striving to be better mentally, socially and emotionally for yourself and your loved ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today&#39;s topic is a bit complicated, but relevant - no offense. And we will end it with a wise saying: &amp;quot;You cannot be lonely if you like the person you are alone with.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 20:44:16 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/the-difference-between-being-alone-and-loneliness/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Finding Inner Peace in a Crazy World</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/finding-inner-peace-crazy-world/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One day you stop fussing and trying to prove something to someone, you look with a smile at the world around you with all its madness, you don&#39;t rush to please people, you don&#39;t rush to give advice or judge or save anyone, you stop answering calls from people who haven&#39;t admired or interested you for a long time, you look at the sky more than at who is busy with what and how they live, you remember what inspires you regardless of the circumstances, you don&#39;t apologize, you don&#39;t explain, you don&#39;t argue, you don&#39;t waste time on the uninteresting and temporary, and you discover incredible peace and many things that you didn&#39;t notice before in the pursuit of meeting someone&#39;s ideas or meeting someone&#39;s expectations.  Comfort within is more precious than any temptations of temporary pleasure. More precious than any temporary people and temporary things. Everything you like is personal, and the personal belongs only to the person you see in the mirror. The rest is empty speculation and conjecture of those who are trying to see something else in you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are your own best ally in how to be yourself and be happy in this crazy world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;em&gt;Tatiana Marach&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/finding-inner-peace-crazy-world/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Stop Doing This: Habits That Kill Success</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/habits-that-kill-success/</link>
        <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop being a people-pleaser. It&#39;s impossible to please everyone, and it&#39;s stressful. It&#39;s better to have a small circle of close contacts than many acquaintances you need to appease. You want to be successful, not a sycophant, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop hanging out with nasty people. Your environment either pulls you up or tramples you further into the ground. Choose who to be friends with and who to surround yourself with practically. Avoid garbage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop watching porn so often (men). Not only is it addictive, but with each orgasm, you lose strength - you ejaculate not only semen but also your motivation. It&#39;s better to save energy and spend your time more wisely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop needing to talk when you&#39;re bored. Don&#39;t know what to do? Don&#39;t call someone for the sake of hour-long conversations about nothing. Instead, read/listen to a book or do something you&#39;ve been putting off for days. Get rid of the need to fill the silence with empty chatter. Fill it with your own depth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop caring about the opinions of others. It&#39;s beyond your control. And if you can&#39;t control it, why worry and fret? It&#39;s a waste of time. Be independent and free yourself from the shackles of approval - they hinder your path to success. Not all your actions will be approved by others, so boldly ignore them. Approve of yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop being in destructive relationships. Does your partner constantly pressure you? Constantly provoke quarrels and scandals? Is there no constructiveness in the relationship? Don&#39;t hope for the best; move on. Break up. Spare your nerves; you&#39;ll need them later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop relying on miracles or luck. 99% of all results depend on your efforts, perseverance, and ambitions. Why would you rot in the shadows for 60 years, hoping for a miracle, if you can create that miracle yourself in a shorter time?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop procrastinating. If you need to do something, do it. Don&#39;t think that tomorrow you&#39;ll find a compromise with yourself and want to do something worthwhile. Do what&#39;s necessary immediately. Don&#39;t deceive yourself, and don&#39;t put obligations in the back burner. By doing this, you&#39;re only delaying your success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 21 Dec 2024 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/habits-that-kill-success/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>4 foundations for self-discipline</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/four-foundations-of-self-discipline/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;1. Too many responsibilities - a destructive break to pieces. Do only what you want to do no matter what. Ignore the irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each commitment that you shoulder affects willpower.
If there is too much excess, it will not stand and you will break.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. Start the day with the most important thing. Something meaningful can be done in the first hour after waking up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don’t want to load yourself with something significant early, do something small. It&#39;s better than just sticking to the phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3. Be sharp and serious about yourself. If you forgot to do something, do not wish yourself, but punish yourself for the offense.
Not with a whip, of course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sacrifice sleep to complete what was promised, for example. So the burden is off your shoulders, and self-confidence increases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4. Routine correction. Plan as much as possible. Stick to the schedule until the very end of the day, do not shirk. When planning, you must take into account your priorities and adhere to their implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more habits and rules you introduce into your routine, the less you have to strain to maintain self-discipline. It will become the same effort as going to the toilet - by default, successful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A strong and reasonable schedule is a must-have for outstanding people. Sooner or later, you still have to take control of the days. And it is better if you come to this yourself, and not forced by circumstances. There will be experience.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2024 08:18:57 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/four-foundations-of-self-discipline/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Self-restraint and sacrifice</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/self-resistaint-and-sacrifice/</link>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It may be that the taste for self-restraint which these creeds, however false, have instilled in mankind has been of some use in strengthening the human race.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the strength of the generic and individual character consists chiefly in the capacity to sacrifice the present to the future, to scorn the temptations of an ephemeral pleasure for a more distant and lasting satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more this faculty is exercised, the more exalted and strong becomes the character; and the highest heroism is attained by those who, in order to preserve or win liberty and truth for other, perhaps distant, ages, renounce the pleasures of life, and even life itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;© James George Frazer
&amp;quot;The Golden Bough&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2024 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/self-resistaint-and-sacrifice/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Success Piramida</title>
        <link>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/success-pyramide/</link>
        <description></description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2024 08:18:57 +0000</pubDate>
        <dc:creator>Vladimir Poplavskij</dc:creator>
        <guid>https://wirtaw.github.io/blog/en/blog/success-pyramide/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
    
    
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>
